we thought to spice it up Geshe Michaels
so dry that we could insert angel devil
debates by you guys every 20 minutes or
so and we were thinking to start one
right off the bat it's are you ready for
done is there a volunteer who is ready
don't ask for volunteers just to sign
them all right and we're gonna start
with one that we just recently workshops
we're gonna start with Alex and Regina
[Applause]
[Music]
hey Regina how are you good
oh yeah you know I'm really not doing
that well though I'm upset about some
work problems that I have what happened
yeah I've just been having a lot of
trouble you know I'm a real real estate
agent yes and I'm having trouble getting
deals to come together that people say
they want to buy they pick out a
property to buy and then they don't
follow through and especially this one
guy he picked out a four million dollar
ranch I'm really excited about it and
then when he came twice flew in looked
at it and then when he were supposed to
talk about it together and he didn't
answer the phone he said he was busy
then we made another appointment to talk
on the phone about writing the offer
[Music]
well you know this is happening with
every piece of property right now I've
got four different people who have
picked out four different pieces of
property and none of them will commit
they say they want to buy it then they
offer too little money and it's just
terrible I'm worried that I'm gonna lose
my job right well I I call them
and I say okay are you ready and I try
to put some pressure on them and I was
thinking about maybe telling them that
that someone else wants the property and
they better hurry up and buy it yeah and
I really don't know what's gonna work
I'm actually really nervous is that
something that could work for me because
I'm really desperate for you you know I
am so responsible about just following
through with everything I think but you
know there is one I do have one bad
habit of not paying a bill on time it's
an internet for my internet at my house
and uh it goes by on the email and I see
it go by and then it just goes over
there and I forget about it and you for
about a month
yeah I could be I can pay my internet
bill right how would that help with my
problem oh but it's the people out there
are the ones who aren't they're not
doing what they should be doing it is it
they're terrible
maybe you can I think you had a lot of
fear to lose my job
I'll get fired
exactly exactly yeah and maybe you can
help someone else who has a similar
problem but there's a there's a shelter
a transitional housing shelter that I
wanted to volunteer at where they help
people who've lost their jobs or their
houses and
give them temporary housing so maybe I
could go there I wanted to go there and
help in fact I said I was going to and
then I didn't show up I think I could do
an hour a week and you know I want to do
it I think I'll try it if you say it
could work I'm willing to try it because
I'm desperate good ok well I'm well I'm
willing to try Thank You Regina nice
which one was the angel okay all right
we're gonna continue with the text and
then we'll take a break somewhere in the
middle and before the break we'll do
another pair and then okay well go like
that all right so the devil just said by
the way this is the segue to the
muhammad' your meditations okay we
haven't had any mom with the meditations
yeah we kind of had a general
description by the angels right and now
the devil says some people say they will
meditate and kick me out they say I will
meditate on the mind as it really is
okay and this is a famous expression in
Tibet you know there are many schools
that said let's meditate on the mind as
it really is okay and then he goes off
on that alright so here we go and again
I think it's weird that the devil is
talking for the whole rest of it just
went to sleep or something okay okay
number one which is verse 94 when you
get to it okay
and again if you want the whole
translation talk to Jigme she just send
it to you by email there's a meditation
that was called no hopes and no no hopes
and no reviewing the past no hopes about
the future and no reviewing the past
okay and it's called just stay kind of
be here now okay it's be here now
anything you know okay just be here now
don't worry about the past
don't worry about things that happened
in the past don't worry about things
that happen to you in the future
just stay it's almost like a present
moment and it's called no complications
and no additions okay and this is the
demos first polka Maha mudra meditations
that don't work okay and he I was
thinking to try to deal with you but I'm
afraid we're getting to have it maybe
I'll just criticize them obliquely okay
let's do that
[Music]
be more fun to try them but you want to
know no okay anyway if someone comes up
to you and says don't think about no
hopes and no regrets it's basically that
you know just be here now and then it's
interesting that the devil critiques the
meditation himself right it's in his
interest that you do it right because it
doesn't contradict him you see I mean
he's interested in meditations that
don't contradict the way he sees things
okay and this is one and and he in the
beginning when he first works through a
few meditations there's 26 right that I
count he kind of tells you why they're
wrong okay so we'll spend a little more
time on the first few and then we'll
spend less time on it because the
critiques are the same all right
so here it is verse 95 but this is
basically just a meditation on your mind
without thinking you know about the
nature of the mind it's just a
meditation on the mind and right now
your mind is defective so the more time
you spend in the present moment with
your defective mind the stuff that was
gonna get okay got it
so if you your right now your mind is
defective why they're related to the two
husband's in the kitchen yeah your mind
automatically thinks that the husband
decided to criticize you you know when
you think of why you're getting
criticized why did the husband call you
stupid instead of giving you a hug okay
then your mind automatically goes to he
he's had a bad day he didn't get enough
sleep something's not going well at his
work you know you blame it on his State
of Mind and this is human nature this is
why we're still here and so he's saying
if you focus your meditation on that
state of mind that state of mind is
defective so the longer you focus on the
present moment of your mind that blames
your husband the more strong the devil's
gonna get okay got it
it doesn't hurt him it fortifies him
okay got it
all right so that theme is going to be
repeated with a number of the 26
attempted [__] meditations to seem
that just by focusing on the mind if the
mind is already making mistakes
you're gonna strengthen that habit okay
again what's the mistake to think that
the husband had a bad day or the
husband's not happy person and he's
attacking you but that's not why he's
attacking you it's coming from your
seeds from in that example what yeah you
yelled at your kids last week
he planted the seeds to hear to see the
husband they opened when you walked in
the kitchen and they opened into your
husband
okay so focusing on the state of mind
with which you enter the kitchen is not
helpful it's not going to do anything to
improve things okay got it all right and
verse 96 he says and this is gonna be a
theme that's repeated and that's called
meditations which don't damage that
first state of mind they don't damage
the opinion they don't hurt the opinion
of the wife who comes into the kitchen
and and he yells and she says he had a
bad day or something's wrong with him
okay
or he decided to yell at me where did
this yelling come come from he decided
to yell at me if you believe that then
how do you treat it you talk to him you
said we gotta talk you know you gotta
respect me I'm not just you know someone
you can yell at all day okay like that
and there's different false approaches
you know I like to joke about them in DC
I talks you know you can refuse him
dinner you can refuse him other things
later on you know but the thing is I
always make a joke you know he's gonna
go for a pizza and and take the pizza
waitress out he'll get both of the
things he wants at the pizza place
yeah you see it can backfire on you if
if a system can backfire on you it's not
a good system you see you want a system
which is fail fail proof fail state tell
Phil sue cannot fail yeah foolproof does
it yeah stupid proof so you by the way
there's a joke in DC I how did the wife
prove she was stupid she yelled back
okay she'll back then what the husband
said turned out to be correct
all right so two common objections to
this that we've already had in the first
rung muhammad meditation number one just
focus on your mind
no know your current state of mind is
defective focus on that and you're just
gonna get more defective okay
then what's the second thing here what's
the second problem with the meditation
it doesn't in any way damage that first
opinion it doesn't even address it you
see the opinion that the husband is
yelling because he had a bad day or he
decided to okay
if a meditation doesn't do any damage to
the opinion that things are coming this
way it is not a useful meditation and if
you want to extend it to your whole day
internal conversations are useless
unless they're talking about season
which means 99% of our own internal
conversations even people who talk about
it all day is are useless
they're just useless there's no point to
them you have wasted your brain boutique
on battery and it's just wasted you know
you're you're conjugating things to do
to get things or to avoid things that
have nothing to do with those things
okay and and if you learn to have an
awareness of how you're thinking right
if you learn to watch the discussion in
your mind you will be dismayed you know
you say oh my god
you know I I've been spending all day
trying to figure out this problem in two
different self existent ways neither of
which is gonna work which means I just
wasted my whole brain capacity for the
whole day you know so if as a result of
these three days classes you can do 1%
see thinking our Alex no sorry Regina
thinking okay if you can think like that
for just one percent of the time your
life will
double your the happy things in your
life the successes in your life will
double if you just give one percent more
time to thinking about seeds okay that's
the that's the effect okay it really is
okay those of us who work for DC higher
you know we spend all day talking about
it
we have what you would call successful
lives but that's just because we're
doing it 1% of the time I can't even
imagine what we have and if you did it
3% of the time but we don't okay we're
also normal people okay all right that's
the two classic complaints about many
[__] meditations number one you
are just focusing on the thought process
and that's not going to improve anything
that's just becoming more aware of your
mind and then secondly it doesn't hurt
that wrong opinion and and there's a big
thing in Buddhism about clear thinking
hurting unclear thinking you see I mean
it's called no Napa right Nick did we
have trouble chanting translating in I
think you could say damage okay so like
a ten minutes of clear thinking damages
an hour of unclear thinking you see it
does something to damage its power you
see it I mean and then and then all
those emotions that flow out of the the
first State of Mind right the negative
state of mind they just kind of bleed
away they just kind of grind down to a
halt you see I mean all other negative
emotions are feeding off the devil if
you hit the devil say geez sage his
killing point right if you strike at the
devil if you strike at the feeling that
things are coming this way and then when
the husband yells at you it's coming
this way if you strike there even just a
feeble you know you know then huge huge
consequences in your life huge changes
in your life okay because all negativity
feeds from that one idea that things are
happening
to you okay got it all right ineffective
I call this as a list of ineffective
meditations okay ineffective military
and ineffective meditation number two
which is verse 97 this is famous
mistaken meditation ineffective
meditation which means by the way I say
ineffective because I don't want to
fight with all the yoga teachers and who
are teaching this you know I just say
look I'm not fighting with you but I
don't think it's very effective okay I
don't want to tell miss just crazy or
stupid you know because I don't want
people calling me crazy and stupid more
so just say it's not very effective okay
the second meditation that the devil
criticizes okay it's emptying the mind
okay empty the mind don't think about
anything okay try to empty the mind you
know try to let go into the void you
know this is not the meaning of the void
at all it has nothing to do with the
meaning of the void it's just the twenty
five century mistake that has been made
over and over and over again okay where
people think emptiness means don't think
about anything you know and I don't know
I don't know it's like I don't know it's
like putting root beer in your gas tank
or something it just it's like it's just
foolish you know it doesn't do anything
it just you know the karmic result of
emptying your mind meditation it's very
interesting in the ancient scriptures
you become forgetful you leave your
phone at different places you can't find
your car keys I hate this new car the
keys not where it should be you just
leave the key anywhere in the car and
then you're gone and then you know I
could have a little holder for the key
where the ignition used to be and then I
know where the key is when I get out of
the cars I mean but this thing of
meditating
and trying to think about nothing.the
karmic result of that is that you become
a spaced out person okay absent-minded
professor you just become kind of
ineffective person okay all right
there was a meditation in Tibet in the
in the panchen lamas time that's sad
okay this is ineffective meditation
number three because I don't want to
calm stupid meditations because that's
an unkind word but they are okay so
number three there was a meditation
where you just focused on how the mind
is not a physical thing okay set the
mind you you close your eyes and you
cancel all the physical stuff in the
room all the colors all the shapes all
the things you can touch and you cancel
them and then what's left in the room is
the mind and you meditate on that okay
so you can imagine you know like you
kind of melt away all the room and the
people and the floor and and the cars
and the parking lot and and the chair
and and you just go into the mind what
would be wrong with them just focusing
on how the mind is not physical what
what problems a it doesn't contradict
the way you misunderstand the husband
you see I mean and to you are focusing
on yeah you are getting deeper in their
mind which is defective okay you're
snuggling up with a defective mind and
it's gonna leak out on you okay got it
you don't want to focus on the current
state of mind which is which is wrapped
up with making a mistake you want to go
into new territory a new state of mind
that says things are coming from me
things that coming from how I treat
people okay all right
in effective meditation number 4 verse
99 okay and and this was a an ancient
meditation from Tibet it was and there
was a big New Age movement in Tibet
thousand years ago okay and it lasted
about 350 years okay and people just did
anything you know all kinds of weird
stuff so then there became a meditation
called meditate on the raw mind the
untouched mind okay like the mind the
essence of the mind go deep to the heart
of the mind and meditate on the center
of the mind okay and that was called raw
awareness it's called Jimba it's the
same word for salad uncooked vegetables
okay so do the uncooked vegetable mind
thing go to the uncooked vegetable your
mind and just hang out there in the
center of the mind okay and that was
called you know like spending time with
your raw awareness okay what problems
same two problems okay it doesn't hurt
the wife's impression that the husband
decided to yell at her it doesn't do
anything to address her misperceptions
you see it I mean it doesn't hurt at all
the root of the problem if the devil the
devil there's a joke later he said I
danced on top of all these meditations I
danced on the person's head while
they're doing them okay okay
number five just let your mind ramble
don't try to control it don't try to
stop it don't try to direct it just
observe it you know let the mind blah
blah and enjoy you know going to deep
state of meditation and listen to the
mind blah blah you can call it blah blah
okay number five blah blah meditation
and and doot and never try to direct or
block thoughts just let them go to their
nature okay same to promise okay same to
promise
yeah there probably happened to you
think you were doing something yeah yeah
it would reinforce ignorance yeah okay
number six he loves our number six - a
lot of uneducated meditations it means
no one trained you
you had an inspiration you know when you
were having french fries and and you
came up with some kind of new meditation
and in the Buddhist tradition it's
foolish not to take advantage of of the
hundred generations of great Lamas you
know of great teachers from the Buddha's
time it's it's foolish to try to
reinvent the wheel
yourself you know there have been like
Cristina cacica yeah how many books in
Mongolia yeah so we have a new project
in Mongolia she raised a million dollars
for we should give her her hand and
there's 200 to 400,000 scriptures here
now call half of them useless which
they're not they're perfect but you know
that leaves 100,000 to 200,000 okay so
at this ineffective meditation number
six the pension Lama says look you know
take advantage of the resources you have
you know and I spend a certain time in
my day Veronica knows like most of the
morning I like to sit with those guys
you know they're dead unfortunately but
I still have their books you know and I
kind of hang out with them in the
morning and I feel like they're there
you know I guess they aren't right and I
just enjoy being with them part of the
day you know and it kind of grounds me
and it gives me comfort somehow it gives
me a deep comfort if I don't get that
hit every day I feel a little weird I
don't feel quite like I'm gonna have a
good day you know so I don't mean like
sit there and study study so boring you
know but sit with those guys you know
just hang out with them read the stuff
lightly you know there's nothing there's
not a single line in any of those
400,000 books which will not bring you
some help and and some comfort and some
wisdom okay so open the stupid book
anywhere and read something you know and
just don't be a fanatic you know like
don't say I what's the third line of the
guards in this 48th verse you know don't
go like that just enjoy hanging out with
these wonderful people and then you're
all day it's kind of more makes more
sense and then when you wake up it kind
of went away again and then just read
some more and the night you know I
remember when I went to the monastery I
got very frustrated because I was from
Princeton right and and I always
understood what was going on in the
class you know I always understood and
then there were
many days in the monastery when I didn't
understand a single thing that the guy
was talking about for two hours you know
and I'm like I can't do this you know
this is really uncomfortable for me you
know I went to my one of my scripture
teachers so I had 12 scripture teachers
and I went to Marla I said I can't do
this you know I can't sit in this class
for two hours and I don't understand a
single thing you're talking about you
know it's really uncomfortable for me
then he said okay I'm giving you this
assignment B assignment B is every other
class you spend it in then in the next
class up if you're a freshman then every
other class you go to a sophomore class
you know that you really don't know what
the hell they're talking about
you know and I'm like I came back this
is the thing about the lowest on the
rabbis advice to the guy he said he
can't stand living with his wife and
kids it's too insane there's no peace
and quiet and the whole house the whole
day and the rabbi said buy a goat and
bring it in the house it's hide it in
the house and keep it in the house you
know and then the guy that keeps the
Gulf in this house for three weeks you
know and then the rabbi calls them again
is this how you doing he says it's worse
it's insane you know the government's
noise oops everywhere eats everything
it's crazy
and the rabbi said okay take the go down
and the guy takes two going on you know
and then the rabbi calls them out to two
days how's your family life it's perfect
everything's perfect it's so nice do you
know it's really nice yeah so tackle
those difficult books you know try to
understand one sentence there it's a
tradition in the monastery that you in
by the way every night in the debate
ground the first half-hour to 45 minutes
you are required to debate with a person
who's two classes up
and you have no idea what is saying you
know and then but when you get there
suddenly it's easy you see what I mean
cuz the seed you planning you see it so
so sit with those guys sit with the
gardener
I sent it out to a lot of you if you
didn't get it talked to Gigi okay I
sending out this morning cos I wanted to
show off I don't really care about your
welfare well I'm hoping it will also
happen it's just opening okay print it
out no can we open it sometimes on the
plane jump yeah okay before you watch a
movie okay yeah and then the movie seems
more interesting okay okay so number six
was the kind of uneducated meditation
you know I'm gonna just make something
up
you know I I got the idea you close your
eyes and you think about something I
sorry I was just gonna design one that
the Buddha didn't think of okay you hear
that a lot
you know I went to a yoga studio near
her mom's house we gotta visit her mom
in Phoenix
every month she goes more often and we
went in we went into the yoga class and
the teachers started teaching Tumlin you
know perfect and yeah I don't know them
they don't know me
I was just sitting there and they said
this is from some guy and I was like
yeah okay okay
meditation number seven this is a
meditation that was popular in Tibet for
hundred years ago and you just go into
your mind and you pretend that
everything's okay like the mind is pure
you know the purity of the mind you know
so yes does your mind blame your husband
when he yells yes but when you meditate
don't worry about it just appreciate
your mind you know the
just decide it's pure you know it's not
pure or you wouldn't have trouble with
your husband in the first place okay but
it's called hiding under the blanket
meditation did you ever notice that kids
do that I don't know did your kids do
that if they're doing something wrong
night like if they're supposed to be
asleep
and you come in and they're playing with
a toy or something they think that if
they put the blanket over them
yeah and they can't see you then then
it's okay you seen I mean so that's you
can call it hiding under the blanket
meditation okay somehow kids you know
you can be standing next to the bed and
looking at them but if they can't see
you then somehow you're not seeing them
you see I mean got it so it would be to
to sit in the mind and pretend the minds
okay when the mind is not okay okay all
right then he says those meditations
that I've given you so far are my holy
deeds you know it took me years to mess
up this mind to where it is now just
give me the credit okay I'm the one I
have messed up the mind in the first
place and I've messed up the meditations
and spread them around the world and
really I should get some credit you know
I'm doing good work better than the
angel wisdom you know like nobody's
doing her meditations everybody's doing
my meditation now I should get some
credit
you know if everyone's doing is wrong
meditations who do you think's fall to
this it's me Sam why okay all right and
saying that saying you're gonna kick me
out of the mind with these things came
on me yeah that's a joke you know
laughing matter
Kamel name means a point of laughter
similar to your name okay your striking
point it's a point of laughter it's a
joke we say it's a joke okay all right
what which one we're on
number eight okay I'm gonna stop Tim it
for and we'll have another debate and
then we'll have refreshments which I'm
sure are here I didn't see them it
worries me okay I'm if they're no good
I'm going home
alright I know they're no good from my
side but it's still the same okay
ineffective meditation number eight and
this is called over-analysis okay taking
the analysis too far like you keep
analyzing and there's several variations
of it okay which is verse 104 105 and
106 okay so verse 104 is focusing on
analysis which is a good thing in
Buddhism you know where I did my husband
really come from analyze what you might
have done to plant the seed for your
husband yelling that kind of analysis is
useful okay but ineffective meditation
number eight is to spend all your time
analyzing other people's mistakes in
meditation which we could easily fall
into right so he says be aware of the
pitfalls traps meditation traps and then
let it go you know don't make that your
meditation okay
don't spend all your time criticizing
the schools which are not as smart as
you are okay and that's the first
version the second version of the same
meditation okay 8a a b 8b is over
analyzing things and not applying it to
you or to your life or to your real
estate company
okay so Buddhism as a study without
being applied to your work it's it's not
Buddhist okay it's not Buddhism okay
just talk about Buddhism and debate
about Buddhism and write books about
Buddhism and then don't apply it at home
in the kitchen when the husband yells at
you or don't apply it to your real
estate company then it's not Buddhism
and a meditation is not a meditation
unless you apply it to your life okay it
be
hc' there's a special variant
it's called analyze the analyzer okay so
you analyze the meditation then you
analyze you okay then you analyze that
you where you came from and then you
analyze the you or the you where the you
came from and it's called infinite
regression okay and that's a meditation
some people do it okay
there's other kinds of meditations that
are similar Kadam Taguchi Duke the
sixteen drops of the Kadamba school
that's very profound you know you go
into a you see a being in your heart and
then you go into the being in their
heart and your going and being in their
heart and you're going to be in their
heart and that has an effect on your
concentration because the smaller the
meditation object the better the
concentration so that's a regression but
it's a youthful one okay this one is
trying to analyze the analyser and then
analyze the analyser the analyser and
then it just gets anal you know and
there's no benefit to it okay apparently
that was popular at some point okay I
could you know in those two hundred
thousand bucks we could find the source
of this if we had nothing else to do but
I have other stuff to do I'm I'm okay to
treat these as generic mistakes that
anybody will make for every couple
hundred years you know they'll be
repeated these mistakes will be repeated
every one hundred years so it's good to
learn all the possible mistakes that
have been made some will apply to you
but many will apply to people that you
teach you see so as a teacher you want
to have a big tool kit right so you know
you study this in the possibility that
you might meet a person who needs to
talk about this one okay so there's a
big emphasis in Buddhism when you're
trying to help other people Bodhisattvas
there's a big deal in shantideva but he
saw us learn how to fix cars
they learn about carburetors they learn
about spark plugs they get interested in
fan belts you know because it might help
someone someday even if you're not
interested in how a car works learn it
you know learn carpentry learn to do
stuff learn how everything at your house
works and learn to fix it okay it's
something we didn't birth count so we
got a merit badge for every electricity
canoe fixing you know but by the time
you ended a goal you gotta have 21 right
it is 21 but you you learn how to fix
everything in your house at the age of
12 or 13 and that's you should because
you buddy stop let's do that kind of
stuff okay buddy something's do that
kind of stuff because it might help
somebody else later so they learn the
twenty-six variations on meditation
mistakes okay all right now I call it
intermission comments okay the devil
makes some intermission comments I don't
know why he's breaks here he takes a
break okay he's about a third of the way
through and he takes a little break to
make some obnoxious comments these are
all wrong meditation objects they're
either picking just the mind with a big
component of misunderstanding in it or
they're meditating on nothing at all or
they meditate on the mind thinking on
nothing at all okay and so to find a
meditation in one of these first eight
which does any damage to me it's like a
star which is bright during the day and
that's a famous Buddhist expression for
impossible okay a star which is like
brighter than the Sun during the day
okay and that's just a famous anemia
karma you know start during the day it
doesn't happen okay
Danny says you are as rare as the cobalt
Lotus okay there's a special blue notice
it opens once once a buna it opens it's
in some paradise it's a special notice
every time a buddha comes to this world
it opens so far in this world for the
last million years there's only been
three or four Buddhist okay it opens as
a as a what he call as a sign that the
Buddha is coming okay
omen yeah this Blue Lotus suddenly opens
in paradise and then everybody says oh
another Buddha's on their way okay so
it's opened like three times in the last
million years he says for someone this
is verse 108 by the way for someone to
suddenly have an insight into why their
husband is yelling at them is as
frequent as a cobalt Lotus okay God and
then he says something very interesting
and he says you may wonder why a cobalt
Lotus realization would suddenly happen
to somebody like what triggered that and
he said proximity to a llama
you know like they're on the same plane
as some llama at a real llama you know a
really wise person and they you know
like they bumped into I ran into the my
logic teacher who's also my yoga tantric
yoga teacher who is also the head of
Gilman Tantra collagen and we'll could
be the next the holder of some Kaaba
strong it's always taken from one of
those two positions um I ran into him at
the baggage area in the San Francisco
right
I just boom we just ran into each other
physically you know okay so if that
happens to you it's a blue cobalt it's a
cobalt Lotus moment okay and in the next
day you might have some insight into why
your husband's feeling okay but it'll go
okay you have to bump into them every
day and it doesn't happen okay so it's
interesting
than in the middle of a philosophical
text the the devil would have the inside
that having a brush with a llama a real
llama is enough that you would
understand briefly why your husband's
healing and then you would forgot again
okay got it
it's kind of beautiful he's kind of
making a statement about guru devotion
which is a big subject of lama chiba
which is the most famous ritual from
tibet and it was written by the same
author it was written by the same month
i think he couldn't hold himself back
from throwing in a little llama devotion
okay got it
he doesn't do it much in the text that
i've finished so far but maybe it comes
later because he calls it the cobalt
lotus springing up in your mind is an
accident caused by a brush with a llama
okay a real number
okay which is cool then he says 109 I am
The King of this mind you know I am The
King he calls the resident Lord I am the
resident of Lord I am the cap dot I'm
the lord of the Madonna
I'm the tantric Lord of this mandala
okay and there's only one thing that can
unseat me and that's the understanding
that the husband is coming from you but
it hasn't happened has it okay like blue
lotuses happen every once well but they
just kind of fade away and Here I am
okay Lord
he calls himself he's like being very
modest Lord of the mandala you know head
of the Buddha families you know it's
called cap doc okay I'm the cap back of
this mind okay it's kind of modesty
isn't one of his faults okay then 110 he
says and I'm gonna probably remain here
because people are resistant to new
solutions
human nature is to resist a really
innovative solution to your life's
problems okay and and we see that with
DCI sometimes we have to tone down a CI
to get more people to come if we really
hit them with the real thing it's like
people get well you know people are
uncomfortable with a radically new
solution even if they can see that the
people teaching it are extremely
successful they they still it's still
hard for them to embrace something
radically new okay and there is a
tradition in Buddhism to water your
message down until the student is ready
it's called the three lower schools okay
okay and Buddha didn't Buddha taught
abhidharma Buddha taught a citrus school
Buddha taught my normal school they're
all teachings of the Buddha but they are
watered down to reach people who resist
radical solutions okay so the The
Devil's saying here people avoid human
nature is to avoid a radically new
solution you know so people feel more
comfortable with the old ones
you know I should talk to my husband I
should with withhold dinner until such
time as he apologizes if it gets really
bad I'll withhold other things and an
hour gained his respect this way see I
mean I will I will fight him for respect
I will demand respect okay and it
doesn't work we all know it doesn't work
it frequently doesn't work and we know
that we all know that but it's more
comfortable to keep doing what we were
doing before
okay it's uncomfortable to embrace a new
solution okay and I think as a teacher
you have to keep that in mind okay like
don't don't grind it in people's faces
you know sometimes they come and say
yeah but can I just talk to my husband
yeah okay yeah okay that'll help yeah I
won't fix him dinner yeah okay do that
try that
in the meantime think about seeds okay
with all the free time you have from not
cooking you know it's called the upaya
what's up aya yeah like trick them you
know yeah yeah don't cook dinner and
during the hour that you saved and think
about seeds okay all right
eight more minutes and then we'll take a
break
ineffective meditation number nine verse
111 okay don't have any concepts and all
in the mind
okay just raw experience okay don't
don't have conceptual thinking avoid
conceptual thinking don't think about
things don't think about solutions don't
think about ideas we need to cool the
room down a little bit we have a
principle in design we keep them
freezing we keep people freezing and
they get sick and this they pay
attention they always they get sick
later they pay attention during the
class starts it's worth it okay sorry
don't think of any concepts go into the
mind and destroy all concepts don't have
any concepts going in the mind he's
gonna talk more about that later okay
actually to understand where the husband
is really coming from requires
conceptual thought if you cancel all
conceptual song in your mind you will
never figure out where the because
figure out means concept okay so his
only comment on this meditation where
you free your mind from all concepts all
thinking about things yes
okay ready this one's so bad I can't
stop laughing about it okay he says that
in that that was like this one it's not
just the K money right it's not just a
joke it's like a it's like a half-hour
show by a really good comedian louis c.k
for a half-hour doing a half-hour comedy
routine you know it's like
can't stop laughing from the moment they
start meditation to the moment they stop
meditating and they're trying not to
think of any concepts which could damage
me since it's so goddamn funny to me you
know so it's so fun to see someone
spending our meditating like that it's
like the most cool thing I can imagine
okay all right one more so when I was
studying Sanskrit at Princeton with a
very esteemed teacher his teacher his
teachers his teacher was Franklin
Edgerton who discovered British sanskrit
hybrid sanskrit and his teacher was
Dwight Whitney who invented sanskrit
grammar in the modern times and he used
to go off on loka okay so there's a verb
there's a verbal root called loach and
then it's also Roch because rnl are
interchangeable in Sanskrit as an
initial so right and lah if you ever
talk to a Thai person you understand
well not really good okay so lo loca
which means the world right the the word
for lo for the world in Sanskrit is loca
but it means the shining okay the word
for the world means the shining and the
idea is that and there's an ancient
theme in Sanskrit grammar or derivation
of words that the world is shining from
your brain your your mind is in lightens
lights up the world your mind lights up
the world so the old word for world is
that which is laid out loca
and the low China is your mind and it is
lighting up the world like the way a
flashlight would light up something
outside at night okay your mind is like
a flashlight so it's kind of similar to
the idea that things are coming from you
okay so there's this idea and it's not
bad
awareness which is almost the same as
life is so much a part of our life from
the moment were born that we don't
notice the awareness you see I mean we
don't notice that we're aware if
something radical happens and you lose
awareness like you're very very ill or
something and you come back then you you
have some appreciation of it but but
every human being mind is lighting up
the world and we aren't aware of it
because it's all the time things that
are happening all the time we aren't
aware of we stop being aware of it's the
same as the conversation in your mind
it's been going on so long that you
don't listen anymore you just let it go
but the world is being lit up by the
mind okay you can call it Sal señorita
Claire annoying definition of the mind
okay definition of awareness so there's
a meditation that someone invented where
you just focus on that fact of awareness
the minds light and you stay in there
you stay in the light of the mind and
they think that's a that's a great
meditation okay you you you you become
aware of the effulgent nature of
consciousness and you sit there in the
light you know the light you stay in the
light got it okay that's number number
ten okay and they think that's the
emptiness of the mind
okay and they also think that's the
meaning of illusion okay somehow but
it's not okay alright okay and it's not
emptiness for sure and you hear people
say that occasionally I saw emptiness
well what's it like Allah is the light
you know there's a oak in the debate
ground there's a 300 year joke this
people still remember some student who
said emptiness is a is a dark green
color
and it's been a joke in the debate
ground since for 300 years like I'd hate
to be the guy who said that and like
nobody knows his name but he's famous
you know yeah the guy who said emptiness
was Green was a green line you know and
but you hear stuff like that you know I
had a Satori
I saw a golden light you know I went
into the golden light it's not a absence
of something it cannot be emptiness it's
a presence of a color it's the opposite
of emptiness it cannot be in tennis but
but P you hear that you hear people say
that so you know that's good to have in
your tool kit to say oh you're having
mistake number 10 go to verse 112 okay
that's that's not emptiness and it's not
useful okay again you are focusing on
the nature of the mind and right now the
nature of the mind is defective the more
close you get to it the longer it's
gonna take you to fix it
okay got it now 113 he makes a side
comment and then we'll take her then
we'll do another internal discussion you
got something in mind Tim okay okay now
113 a slight comment by the demo a very
very insightful one okay as I said real
Devils are not stupid you know CS Lewis
says don't go looking for people horns
okay
real Devils are the people who say you
know I respect your I respect that you
went this afternoon into the class I
respect that you want to review it you
know it's it's a good thing it's just
that the restaurants having is special
tonight and there's a wine that you
can't get any other nine and and I agree
the the study is important I think it's
a good thing I'm glad you're doing this
Buddhism thing it's a good thing but but
you know you can't do it all the time
you know let's just go out tonight and
you you you you hit it tomorrow morning
okay and CSS that's that's the devil
okay
the devil is sophisticated elegant
intelligent you know cosmopolitan the
devil's not a fool the devil doesn't
ever look like the devil okay got it
now at this point the devil is so
sophisticated and he says you know what
would mess me up but it's never gonna is
if someone understood that I'm not that
I don't come from either you know if
anyone ever got it then I'm also coming
from from their sins
now that would mess me up but that's
it's not gonna happen he's like very we
call cynical but it's right right this
is he's just like he makes an offhand
comment you know verse 113 he's like you
know it wouldn't mess me up he's been
talking about
lokah right like deal with a fulton
awareness you know and then he says he's
like just thinking out loud burst 113
and he's just you know it would really
mess me up if anyone ever figured out
that I was coming from their seats but
you know who's gonna do that you know
and then he goes on to 114 okay
and by the way 114 marks a segue into a
series of meditational mistakes based on
the idea of empty space okay so there's
a important Buddhist meditation called
space like meditation and I took this
section and turned it into a meditation
called the four spaces meditation I took
this section and turned it into a forced
basis meditation because the three of
them seem like emptiness but are not so
I threw in the real one and the three
that people mistake for emptiness and I
blunt them all together so if you take
this thing I don't know what level this
seven you did you do these three wrong
ones
based on space empty space because
people over centuries have mistaken them
for four the real one and then you do
the real one okay so and it's was it was
really hard to teach the teachers cuz
they kept getting confused you know like
well what's number three was number two
you know what's and this is where it
comes from
okay because the devil is happy that
people have mistaken the word space like
meditation for empty space or other
kinds of space okay so I'll tell you the
first one cuz it's super stupid and this
is an old Dobby Dharma mistake okay
space like meditation is blue you focus
on blue because the sky is blue okay so
the word for space number Akasha Akasha
the word in Sanskrit or Tibetan is it's
the same for outer space and blue space
and the space that our object occupies
those three kinds of space the word in
Buddhism is the same so that's a problem
and there's a word for space used for
emptiness okay so it's four kinds of
space this is where the discussion
begins okay and it's good to go through
them so you don't get caught thinking
that one of them is emptiness when it's
not so the obvious one is emptiness not
blue sky okay when they call em Venus
meditation space like meditation they're
not referring to space in the sense of
the canopy over the earth that's blue
okay
that one's easy I'll give you the easy
one for free okay Tim you ready I'm
hungry I mean I want to hear the next
debate next group is going to be Aaron
and Nick
let's give them a round of applause and
token if we need you we need the
microphone Jim okay
Hey how's it going
it's gone okay uh-huh doesn't look like
everything's going okay is everything
all right it's fine what's wrong it
seems like something's wrong oh well to
be honest something came up at work
we had a contract with one of our
clients and just doesn't seem like
they're gonna pay the whole thing man
that's rough what are you gonna do I
[Laughter]
have an idea
oh I have an idea I think I'm gonna
write like a threatening and angry email
I'm gonna threaten to sue I'm gonna tell
him you're breaking the contract I'm
gonna come at him with everything we got
I'm gonna scare him what do you think oh
I see like in the movies right it always
works just sue him yeah that always gets
the money right maybe I won't do that
unless all right I got it you just gotta
you know you got a reason with him just
be practical just lay it all out and if
you put it all in the right words he'll
pay you you know I got an idea I'm gonna
use logic I'm gonna reason with him I'm
gonna just speak to him rationally I'm
gonna lay it out just how it is
and if I do it like that he's definitely
gonna pay you know I'm just gonna
explain to him visit the situation if we
don't get this exact amount of money the
company can't even function I think as
long as he understands that he's totally
gonna pay right oh my gosh you're so
right every time I use like reasoning
like
rational thinking with someone they
always do what I want don't you have
that same experience well you know I am
married I think I catch what you're
saying yeah yeah doesn't always work you
ever have to think about this a little
bit more I don't know I have an idea you
should tell him all of the things that
are gonna happen if you don't get that
money
explain to him you're gonna your kids
what are your kids gonna do they have to
eat your wife your mom who's sick you
got to make him have pity on you oh I
got an idea
I totally have an idea I'm gonna write
him a letter and I'm gonna explain I'm
gonna make him feel sorry for us I'm
gonna explain my mom is sick and the dog
has to go to the vet and the kid little
Jimmy needs a new foot I gotta explain
to him everything you know and then he's
gonna feel sorry for us and he's totally
gonna want to give us the money right
that's a good idea
hold on hold on a second you think if
you make him feel sorry for you and have
pity on you then he's gonna want to give
you all his money no okay I have this
idea it's totally out of left field and
it's not even related to what we're
talking about but um have you ever
thought about whether or not you
actually pay your bills on time or pay
people who you owe of course I always
pay people who I owe on time except for
the catering company that was just that
was a couple weeks ago though and you
know why only a few weeks later on it is
what I mean and but other than that I
always pay my bills on time except for
that production company who does our
events and
okay I see where you're going with this
I'll take that into consideration good
idea thank you no problem so it's great
to see you here in Sedona how are you
just going back where you work and live
it's a struggle yeah yeah what's going
on well I just have this boss and she is
she just doesn't listen to anybody and
she just wants to do it all her way and
she disrespects other people and I just
feel like I'm unwanted there and there's
no gratitude and wow it's really hard
really hard what are you what are you
doing about it well I tried to talk to
her and I talked to other people about
her I complain we all commiserate well
not all of us but some of us commiserate
together so do you think everybody sees
this woman the same way no she could saw
him with other people really well yeah
it's like why doesn't she get home with
me but she doesn't get on with a few
other people too right
it appears that way yeah sorry you ever
talked to them about and try to help
them through their day yeah okay that's
nice yeah yeah thank you
so anything changed any improvement oh
you know what yeah after I well I'm a
little embarrassed to say this but go
ahead we're friends I got I felt like a
pressure cooker and things kept building
up and then one day I just exploded at
her and I basically threw a temper
tantrum temper tantrum yeah and then
things got better
real things got better after that better
after that yeah she started consulting
me and I felt like I was being listened
to and things got better right great so
have you had a lot of luck in your past
with temper tantrums a fair amount
always every time it works no once I got
grounded Oh Holly wants huh right once
that I remember but you know we don't
necessarily like to remember those kinds
of things we don't but it sounds like
anger may not be an effective way of
addressing this woman and her problems
with you well it works a good part of
the time sometimes right and there was
an improvement ya know the temper to him
and you're pretty sure it was as a
result of that temper tantrum yes
so did you ever consider that maybe you
said you talked with some of the people
there about their bad days with this
woman do you think maybe the improvement
could have had another cause I guess
it's possible hmm anything's possible
mm-hmm you're gonna think about that
yeah I'll try that out all right
[Applause]
okay what questions any questions we
could have fun yeah I wanted to ask you
about number seven so verse 102 which is
going to your mind and pretend that
everything is okay and believe you have
the pure mind and the Nima's I believe
teach pure from the side of your already
pure and you just need to recognize that
and so I wondered what the difference
between this and what they teach of
being a pure mind earlier we had the
angel saying that you did have an
inherent party of mine which is your
Buddha nature so I think that's where
that tradition comes from and I think
it's it's probably grounded on a correct
thing you know I you know every
tradition including the one where people
have taken correct statements and made
weird traditions out of them and it
happens to everybody it happens to all
traditions but I think the basis of it I
don't think this is talking about done I
think that's probably well founded in
the idea that the emptiness of view or
of your mind is the basis of your
enlightenment and so I think that's
probably a good tradition of course some
people probably didn't understand it and
made it weird but they've done that with
everything probably they'll do it with
this text then I'd somehow you know it's
not very clear what this one but he
calls it pretend misunderstanding
doesn't exist
so it's like somehow you recognize it
and you pretend it's not there okay so
um that's all the a lot of these we
don't have more information about them I
think what a translator should do is try
to find an archetype which fits that
description you know like a typical
mistake that many people make and I
guess you could say kind of this
cheerful thing where people say you're
all right just recognize you're all
right and don't worry about it and you
know your problem is that you think
something's wrong with you but really
everything's fine and you're okay and
just recognize that you're okay and
things will be all right okay which is
not true okay all right how's that other
question thank you for teaching geshe-la
and this kind of is related to summers
question but um I can't recall the the
number of the meditation but it was
about the nature of the mind and and
described as being clear and aware and
and there's no mistaken concept in the
qualities clear and aware and so I'm
wondering how that one fits supporting
the devil yeah good okay that the theory
presented at the beginning of the whole
string of meditations is that if you
just focus on the mind you're focusing
on something which has an inherent
mistake in it that's always been
mistaken so it might reinforce it if you
just meditate on the fact that the mind
is aware that's somehow and it's true
there's no you would think it was a
neutral meditation it'd be like
meditating on a stone or something that
it's made of rock or something and it
shouldn't hurt you but you know I think
the argument is that the longer you
don't recognize the nature of your mind
the more ingrained it come becomes and
that's almost shades into shanty Davis
accusation that you are hurting seven
billion people because you didn't get
enlightened today but that's a little
too much okay one more
so first 106 analyzing the analyzer yeah
in this infinite regression doesn't that
have a value of because of that
regression you can get to a realization
that it never ever really existed yeah I
think it could be used that way yeah I
think he's criticizing stopping there
and just or keeping going and just uh I
when i read the tibetan it feels like he
was criticizing someone who was trying
to be cute and saying look you could
find them look her at the looker and you
can find a looker at the looker at the
looker and they and it just went on and
on and it didn't resolve and the person
didn't intend to resolve it it felt like
he was criticizing someone who was
trying to be cute veronica has a
question that manny left with us because
he had to catch a plane he asks last
night you described how a continuous
flow of karma creates a special form of
karmic arising that doesn't start peak
and fade away but rather is a constant
arising that has always been and will
always be as i understand it karma
arises in the mind this seems to be
circular logic to me ie the mind
creating itself my understanding is that
a thing can't come from itself can you
please explain yeah okay this is called
the cocoon question in chimera Sheila
okay
and it's that if I do something in the
morning and then I do something after
noon and I do something in the evening
is that those seem to be three different
things right
there's Michael's mind in the morning
Michael's mind in the afternoon and
Michael's mind in the evening and then
there's an argument against the idea
that there's no soft nature which says
if there's no Michael then Michael
cannot experience the results of his
deeds
you see if Michael hurts somebody on
Tuesday and Michael gets a result on
Wednesday well there has to be a self
called Michael because it isn't that all
power gets heard on Wednesday when
geshe-la makes a mistake on Tuesday so
there must be some common denominator
between Michael on Tuesday and Michael
on Wednesday and that common denominator
should be a self existent thing you know
and then Kamala Sheila gets asked this
question okay and then he says that's
true but your seats connected to okay
and then he compares it to a cocoon he
says your seats start a cocoon on
Tuesday and in the cocoon on Wednesday
you see I mean so your seats you have
connectors needs that connect Michael on
Tuesday to Michael on Wednesday and
that's a separate karmic ripening of
Michael over time so there's a something
glues Michael together from Tuesday
morning to Wednesday afternoon and
that's also coming from seeds so some
schools of ancient India have said
because karma is is experienced from
what you did before then then Michael
must exist independent of karma
but then Camila she was like no that
proves karma because Karma's the thing
that when he can't glues together the
Michael on Tuesday and the Michael on
Wednesday
Michael's mind is also a gluing together
and and there's two kinds of emptiness
there's the emptiness of a pen which is
the fact that something is gluing the
pieces together in a static moment in a
single moment but then there's the
emptiness of Michael over time so when
you're discussing the pen you break down
the pieces of the pen okay when you're
discussing Michael you break down the
moments of Michael's stream the stream
of Michael and that's also empty okay so
there are streams of there are moments
of consciousness but what ties them
together is a seed coming from your mind
and I like to talk about Alzheimer's me
and David we're talking about
Alzheimer's we decided that the sign
that you have Alzheimer's you can't
remember what the word means but if
those seeds fail you get a discontinuity
in your consciousness you can't remember
what happened this morning
or you can't remember your own children
you know you there's a karma for
continuity there's a different separate
Karma for being continuous over time and
so it's not the case that in the
mornings mind is the same as the mind in
the afternoon they're not the same thing
the mornings mind has created the mind
in the afternoon but by making seeds
that glue it to the mine in the
afternoon cool and that the question
about emptiness being coming from your
seats okay that's a problem I'll repeat
it again and I'll go at it from a
different angle here's a famous angle
the mind is known in Buddhism to change
instant by instant even if you're not
married you still can understand that
okay or you don't have certain sponsors
or whatever things change
wait we just fixed that problem
I take it back so things change instant
instant right and there's a debate about
the direct perception emptiness because
emptiness is constant and cannot change
it never changes its quality never
changes but the call of the mind is
super changing like even more than other
things
it is moments of Santana so before the
band there was a Sanskrit name called
Santana and it means that moments of
consciousness coming one after another
and and it's very changing in quality
every moment so but then the question
comes how can a mind whose nature is to
constantly be in and out and like this
how can it focus on an unchanging thing
you know how it's not even possible okay
and then and then if you say aren't
there things that don't come from coming
seeds because aren't there things that
don't change and isn't it true that all
things that come from seeds get bigger
and then decline you know isn't it true
that there's this sign with with all
things that change so how can emptiness
if a person's in the direct perception
of emptiness how can it be that their
mind sees are creating the emptiness
like the second like the first husband
in the kitchen how can it be that the
mind that's perceiving emptiness
directly is producing that emptiness
from its seeds in the way your mind
produces the husband the real has been
in the kitchen okay
because wouldn't that mean that
emptiness changes from instant to
instant and there's a difference between
the word change and constant constant in
its quality okay constant in its quality
it's different from the idea of change
okay so is there a two-headed purple
elephant in this room full size there
isn't okay
now that's that lack of a two-headed
purple elephant in this room ever get
more or less does it vary no because if
it did you'd have his foot would appear
you see if he was less gone then he was
five minutes ago that if he was less
gone it would mean parts of him would
start to appear if he was more gone then
we couldn't even imagine a purple out
you see I mean he doesn't get more or
less gone he's just gone okay and then
in the monastery you know the kids that
the 13 year olds in the debate ground
who always cause trouble they're like
when if the elephant is halfway in the
room but he's halfway down the room you
know we get these arguments anyway
absences can be constant because if they
were not constant then little pieces of
the elephant would show up in the room
got it
okay so emptiness is constant but it's
but the same pattern is repeating over
and over it doesn't get more on this
okay and it's still coming from your
mind okay or else or what's the fault of
saying it doesn't come from your mind
then emptiness would not have emptiness
okay then emptiness would not have
emptiness and all things must have em
okay got it
alright let's do a little more for fun
and we'll just do it for good luck okay
we have like seven more minutes all
right
okay I here's a few more silly ones okay
so ineffective meditation number 11
meditate on an empty space okay and
that's so let's go through the four
kinds of space okay maybe that's a good
place to start
okay because next he's going on to the
most important meditation on emptiness
which is one and many but you could also
say parts and halls okay so that's a
good place to start in March okay March
1st 2nd and 3rd same place I kind of
like it here in this room do they write
the check couch is more comfortable the
food is more comfortable okay so let's
just decide if we're all around okay
so there's four kinds of space okay the
problem came because Nam collaborating
is insane Nam car Bobby's pinions in
meditation that is similar to space
based like meditation okay so what I
like to do is instead of fighting with
people don't do the wrong space
meditation I did something clever I
think it was clever always second clever
right be so rather than keep reminding
people and correcting people I require
them to do all form you know then they
they don't mess up okay so here's a
meditation you can do we teaching in DC
our level I don't know
so we first with em and we take you up
on a grassy knoll which is near Beaver
Creek actually where we once had a
meeting if you remember grassy place and
you go there and you lay down on your
back and you look at this guy okay and
it's important not to have any trees in
your line of sight
so you're just looking at the blue sky
so that's the first meditation on space
which is you know the word again the
word for sky in the word for outer space
and the word for absence of place is the
same in sounds good in Tibetan okay num
color or Akasha so in the meditation you
lie on your back on a nice green field
and you you just look at the blue sky
okay and that's you know it's calming
does it hurt the devil no okay
then you imagine that this also comes
from experience we had you imagine that
it's getting dark okay like you're out
in the woods and it's getting dark so
then the sky gets more gray the blue
turns to shifted gray and you're still
staring at the blue it shifts to gray
and then it goes to black okay and then
you're kind of looking at what outer
space okay in English we call it outer
space so again in Tibetan and Sanskrit
the word is the same
okay so rather than looking at the blue
canopy you're imagining the place where
the stars sit okay the black velvet
where the stars sit okay endless
infinite outer space okay and that if
you do these four spaces in a row it
kind of sets you up for the real one
it's not bad it's not bad so then you
meditate you just on your back
it turned nine and you're staring at the
black okay and that's the second meaning
of space okay which is the outer space
okay the place between planets okay then
you can shift to ready the place where
your body is resting okay I don't mean
the grass under your back
I mean the space your occupier okay
the space you are occupying okay which
is empty that's that's real
philosophical empty space and it cannot
be perceived with the eye it cannot be
perceived with these two eyes you need
the third eye of logic so you it can
only be perceived to a process of logic
you know the place you are occupying
right now okay
the place the space you are occupying
right now okay and I don't mean the
absence of air okay and then what are we
always saying this a do you remember at
this point we say it's not like
displacing water in a bathtub
it's not that okay it doesn't mean that
it doesn't mean if I move over there
oxygen molecules have to get out of the
way you see any it doesn't mean that it
means the space I occupy philosophically
speaking is empty okay if it weren't I
could I cannot enter this space you see
because it's occupying that space so
it's exclusive you can somebody only one
thing can be in and at the same time
okay so that lack of they call toxic
topic member toorak kappa yeah they
caught ya asanga lack of obstruction
it's a sanga's name because his mind was
such as unstoppable it means unstoppable
okay so you know there's it's occupying
space now a test if you're teaching this
to your students okay a test to see if
they got it right is to ask them if they
blew up this planet you know which you
know if we work hard we can do it if we
blow up the whole planet into dust you
know would this space that the chair is
occupying would it remain or not it
would okay it wouldn't be on the planet
anymore the dust would be going you know
go everywhere
but that space would always be there
okay
in that sense okay if you want to go
deeper okay Shanee in that sense not
forgotten that's the space will stay if
everything is destroyed Oh
in that sense empty space which is the
third space now okay we had blue sky we
had black outer space both visual and
now we have theoretical space that's
almost equivalent to location
it's almost equivalent to location you
see this is occupying a location so
those coordinates right XY and z axis
will not change if this planet blows up
you know and even as the whole galaxy
moves away from the Big Bang that
location in theory right those three
lines intersecting that will always be
here that will stay here okay so that's
that's empty space okay all right so now
so far we have sky outer space in
English terms okay
sky outer space and empty space okay the
third one has often been mistaken for
emptiness and that's the point of the
text here okay because meditation number
11 verse 114 the other guy
misunderstands the reference space like
meditation nam kitab athenians and he
misunderstands the meaning of space
flight and it takes it to mean empty
space okay what are that well what's the
problem what what's wrong with that
minute area
it does nothing to hurt the devil okay
it doesn't touch him at all but I think
it can be twisted into a useful
meditation if you if you take the person
to the next one okay so that's why I
like to teach the four together because
people avoid making the first three
mistakes okay so oftentimes it's useful
to teach someone a mistake in meditation
so they can experience it and that's
what he's doing here with the book he
wants us to go through the list of
mistaken meditations in case one day we
go to a class and someone tries to talk
us into this is meditation
this is emptiness okay then we'll
remember oh no that's that was number
fourteen you know that's just number
fourteen that's not an emptiness
meditation okay okay the last one is
what I like to do is sit I'm still on my
back I like to teach the meditation as
you're still on your back because it
keeps people calm you know there's no
movement you're still laying on your
back you know and then think about the
planet behind your back okay think about
the planet that's touching the skin on
your back right and where I didn't who
made the planet you see and then people
will say oh there was a big bang it was
like throwing a pie in most or curly
space and little pieces of pie flew
everywhere and then we're just on one of
those pieces the the piece behind your
back that's that's piece of pie going
out infinitely after the big bang
it's just another piece of the Big Bang
so it you know it was kind of created by
the Big Bang who made the Big Bang you
know and eventually it's it's kind of
cool to lead a student into the question
of if all things are coming from them
and you know you can call it a Big Bang
you just can't call it unique you can't
call it a singularity that's a mistake
but there could have been a
bang you know that was triggered by a
small and another bang before that's
okay but who created the one I think
it's 50 million years ago
I mean who created that one who did that
one according to us who did that one
yeah you did then I think it's useful to
teach people you know the pin is okay
right depends okay teach the pin that's
coming from you teach the husband who's
yelling at us coming from you but if
your students want to go deeper explore
if the Big Bang is coming from you okay
and in the end you have in this school
you have to say it is does that imply I
was there yes I mean you can the memory
of the Big Bang you know the logical
conclusion that there was a big bang
that's a current event but the original
Big Bang 50 million years ago if that's
the right number and remember 50 billion
oh sorry I was there and I did create it
okay it is a it was a it was a present
perception at the time okay
it was I was there you see and you can
lead people back there it's kind of cool
you see you didn't just create your your
wife or your husband and you didn't just
create the pin but the earth you're
standing on you also created it okay
you're also creating a dud you must have
okay got it
okay so the emptiness the fourth space
is an easy way to teach it okay if
you're in a group of 500 or 5000 3000
people ask everybody to raise their hand
I like to say left hand because it's a
tantric thing I say raise your left hand
everybody raise on the hem and then I
say really point your first finger and
they say point your first ring and then
I say point to one thing in this room
that
not coming from you from your seat and
then when you're teaching it you can go
like drama you can go I like to go this
way at the end okay and that's emptiness
okay then they reached emptiness okay
that's all
it's called tandem epi' it's a it's a
Buddhist method of reaching young penis
it's called tandem fr this tennis bsta n
which means cannot be demonstrated you
could point to you cannot point to a
thing that is not coming from your mind
and in that way you reach emptiness any
a crowd of a thousand people can get
pretty close to emptiness with this
little finger thing
first finger okay got it
it's kind of cool so the fourth space is
the again it's a space you cannot see
with your eyes do you see it with your
third eye and it's it's it's what's left
when you're looking for things you
didn't create okay
it's what it's what you come to at the
end which is a special kind of nothing
okay got it
and that's Kate of Jays thing if you're
Internet
okay alright so that's a useful way to
see step four spaces next time we'll
pick up at one six one seventeen and
he's about to go into a correct Buddhist
meditation called one or many
and that's basically founded on the
first chapter of Nagarjuna well which
again I encourage you to chew on it's
something you can definitely spend some
useful hours with until March okay and
you will be confused and you will say
this sounds ridiculous you know this
guy's like drunk or something you know
you will think that but but I urge you I
beg you keep at it
just chip away at it a Sangha the second
time he quit and left men his retreat
yeah but was the other one I like the
other one no the one I was before that
it was the first one yeah there was a
guy with an anvil there was a guy with
an anvil between his leg you know this
is how they fix shoes in India they hold
him with their feet he's got an anvil
between his feet and he's robbing at it
with a cotton cloth and and the Sangha
just left his retreat cave and he said
to hell with this you know for four
years I think three years three years
and he he meets this guy at the bottom
of the mountain what what it just looks
a business with old guises I'm just
making a needle yeah now that's
persistent you know and he gets ashamed
and he turns around and he goes back to
the cave okay got it
so while you're trying to read in the
garden ah it's like rubbing at an anvil
with a soft cotton cloth alright but but
just do it I swear you'll your mind will
explode in a good way
okay just dig it dig at it don't stop I
think you guys are ready
you had the background and it'll seem
confusing and then hang in there and
he's not repeating himself and he's not
and it none of it is BIA
it's all extraordinary okay and I
believe the sign that he really was in
Arya is that he only uses simple words
and he writes in poetry and he he always
writes in poetry and they're weird
poetry the GAO is not the gun the guy's
not carry the greatness you know he's
just like it's like a song but he never
uses big words it's very similar to
Jesus and in a way he never uses
philosophy he uses tiny short
words and your and I believe that's a
sign that he was an aria you know
because he's so with with four lines at
that you can see you can fruitfully
spend a month on it okay so go for it
okay alright see you in March I'd like
to thank Tim and jing-mei for working so
hard
[Applause]